<?xml version="1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
    <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-noneoc">noneoc_0011</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Hartwick Seminary Record Group</titleproper>
                <author>Wallace, Shelley</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <date normal="1739/1940">1739/1940</date>
                <address>
                    <addressline>Hartwick College</addressline>
                    <addressline>Oneonta, New York 13820</addressline>
                </address>
                <publisher>Hartwick College</publisher>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Hartwick Seminary Record Group</unittitle>
            <unitdate normal="1739/1940">1739 - 1940</unitdate>
            <physdesc>
                
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>          The documents in this record group span the years 1739 through 
1940.  The records were not received in a specific order and many were accessioned at different times.  Thus, they have been arranged to best reflect the organization and history of the seminary.  They are divided into twelve series:
     
I. Dudde Collection
II. H.C. Collection
III. Day Collection
IV. Yale Collection
V. Board of Trustees
VI. Course Records
VII. Societies
VIII. Publications
 IX. Memorabilia
 X. Hartwick Academy
 XI. Photographs, Maps, Graphics
 XII. Bibliographical Information
     
     The first four series contain related letters and land deeds during 
John Christopher Hartwick's years in America and the establishment of the institution after his death, with the bulk of the material dating between 1796 and 1878.
          The remaining series document life at the seminary.  Although the records are not always complete they do delineate a clear picture of the struggles and growth of the seminary and the flavor of campus life.

</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <acqinfo>
            <p>          This collection includes the papers of or relating to Rev. John 
     Christopher Hartwick and the establishment of the Hartwick 
     Seminary.  The documents reflect the life of John Christopher 
     Hartwick, his work with the Lutheran Synod, his land dealings, the 
     problems of executing his will and establishing the Seminary, the 
     relationship of the Lutheran Synod with the Seminary, the academic 
     and social life of the Seminary and its eventual division into 
     Hartwick Academy, Hartwick Seminary and Hartwick College.
          Hartwick College received many of the records directly from 
     Hartwick Seminary including a ten volume series compiled by Rev. 
     John H. Dudde.  There have been numerous accessions from alumni and 
     friends, including two major collections, one from Mr. &amp; Mrs. Robert 
     G. Day and the Rev. John Kunze Papers from Yale University.   There 
     are detailed calendars and some transcriptions of these collections.  
</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <bioghist>
            <p>John Christopher Hartwick (1714 1796) was born in Molschleben, in the Duchy of Saxe Gotha, Germany and educated at the University of Halle.  He arrived in America in 1746, an ordained Lutheran 
minister.  He was a very eccentric man with a rigid personality and little tolerance of people's vices.  He frequently required his parishioners to sign a covenant that "they would forswear shooting, horse-racing, boozing, and dancing."  His inability to find a congregation willing to submit to his strict dictates, only confirmed Hartwick's belief that American society needed to be reformed by regulating settlement patterns and enforcing a disciplined code for each community.  To this end he made numerous land deals and eventually was successful in obtaining the majority of a 24,000 acre patent from the Indians in Otsego County, New York.  He died in 1796 without having fulfilled his dream for a "New Jerusalem," but left complete instructions in his will for the organization of a seminary.  However, the executors of his will, Jeremiah 	Van Rensselaer and Frederick A. Muhlenberg had difficulty enacting 
Hartwick's wishes because he had designated Jesus Christ as his heir.  The executors did manage to get through numerous legal problems and founded Hartwick Seminary, the first Lutheran Seminary in America, in September 1797 but postponed the decision on the final location of the school.  Dr. John Christopher Kunze was named director and taught theology at his home in New York City, Rev. Anthony Braun taught sciences and languages at Albany and Rev. John Frederick Ernst taught elementary school on the Hartwick Patent.  There was great debate about the permanent location of the seminary but due to the persistence of the residents of the Hartwick Patent the first seminary building was established there in 1815 and Rev. Ernest Lewis Hazelius became the first principal.  The seminary offered an academy and a theological department. In 1816 it was incorporated with 12 trustees appointed, the majority of whom were to be Lutheran clergymen.  During the first 20 years the school averaged between 60 and 70 students.  The enrollment dropped nearly in half in the late 1830's and 1840's.   Women were admitted for the first time in 1851 bringing the enrollment to 89 and in the 1880's it was over 100.  In 1888 the Classical Department introduced the Freshman year of a Collegiate Course and in 1927 it expanded to a 4 year college and was moved to Oneonta, New York.  The Theological Department took the name Hartwick Seminary when it moved to Brooklyn, New York in 1930. 
     The Seminary closed in the spring of 1940 and consolidated with Hartwick College in 1947.  The Academy remained on the original location  until 1934 when classes ceased.
     
John Christopher Hartwick (1714 1796) was born in Molschleben, 
     in the Duchy of Saxe Gotha, Germany and educated at the University 
     of Halle.  He arrived in America in 1746, an ordained Lutheran 
     minister.  He was a very eccentric man with a rigid personality and 
     little tolerance of people's vices.  He frequently required his 	parishioners to sign a covenant that "they would forswear shooting, 	horse-racing, boozing, and dancing."  His inability to find a congregation 	willing to submit to his strict dictates, only confirmed Hartwick's belief 	that American society needed to be reformed by regulating settlement 	patterns and enforcing a disciplined code for each community.  To this end 	he made numerous land deals and eventually was successful in obtaining the 	majority of a 24,000 acre patent from the Indians in Otsego County, New 	York.  He died in 1796 without having fulfilled his dream for a "New 	Jerusalem," but left complete instructions in his will for the 	organization of a seminary.  However, the executors of his will, Jeremiah 	Van Rensselaer and Frederick A. Muhlenberg had difficulty enacting 
     Hartwick's wishes because he had designated Jesus Christ as his 
     heir.  The executors did manage to get through numerous legal 
     problems and founded Hartwick Seminary, the first Lutheran Seminary 
     in America, in September 1797 but postponed the decision on the 
     final location of the school.  Dr. John Christopher Kunze was named 	director and taught theology at his home in New York City, Rev. Anthony 	Braun taught sciences and languages at Albany and Rev. John Frederick 
     


INVENTORY   2
     
     

	Ernst taught elementary school on the Hartwick Patent.  There was 
     great debate about the permanent location of the seminary but due to 
     the persistence of the residents of the Hartwick Patent the first
     seminary building was established there in 1815 and Rev. Ernest 
	Lewis Hazelius became the first principal.  The seminary offered an 
     academy and a theological department.  In 1816 it was incorporated
	with 12 trustees appointed, the majority of whom were to be Lutheran 
     clergymen.  During the first 20 years the school averaged between 60 
     and 70 students.  The enrollment dropped nearly in half in the late 
     1830's and 1840's.   Women were admitted for the first time in 1851 
     bringing the enrollment to 89 and in the 1880's it was over 100.  In 
     1888 the Classical Department introduced the Freshman year of a 
     Collegiate Course and in 1927 it expanded to a 4 year college 
	and was moved to Oneonta, New York.  The Theological Department took the 
     name Hartwick Seminary when it moved to Brooklyn, New York in 1930. 
     The Seminary closed in the spring of 1940 and consolidated with 
     Hartwick College in 1947.  The Academy remained on the original 
     location  until 1934 when classes ceased.
     
</p>
        </bioghist>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
